

_ouis **Lippens**

Ghent University (FEB), Sint-Pietersplein 6, 9000 Gent, Belgium

☑ Louis.Lippens@UGent.be | 备 louislippens.be | ☑ Louis-Lippens | ☑ lglip | 🛅 louislippens

About Me

I am a joint PhD researcher in labour economics and sociology of labour at Ghent University and Vrije Universiteit Brussel with an interdisciplinary background and a pronounced interest in data visualisation. My present work focuses on the determinants of and contextual factors contributing to (ethnic) hiring discrimination. More broadly, I research labour market topics relating to hiring and selection and labour demand and supply. I have previously worked for consulting firms on data governance, data analytics, and HR projects. I have also obtained a master's degree in work psychology and a business degree in general management.

Employment

ACADEMIA (FULL-TIME)

Ghent University Ghent RF

Aug. 2019 - Present DOCTORAL RESEARCHER

- · Research on topics in labour economics, contributing to solving societal questions surrounding the (Belgian) labour market
- · Teaching assignments, such as guiding last-year students with their master's thesis, coaching bachelor students on migration research topics, and giving guest lectures on empirical/experimental economic research
- · Development of low-threshold, interactive, and flexible tools (e.g. multicultural situational judgment tests) to increase the awareness of HR professionals' intercultural competence and to empower them to deal with the drivers of their competence
- · Dissertation: research on (ethnic) hiring discrimination, its determinants, its mechanisms, and the influence of the organisational context

Vrije Universiteit Brussel Brussels, BE

VISITING DOCTORAL RESEARCHER

Aug. 2019 - Present

· Research on topics in sociology of labour

PRIVATE SECTOR (FULL-TIME)

BDO Ghent/Antwerp/Brussels, BE

SENIOR CONSULTANT (DATA ANALYTICS)

- Oct. 2018 Jul. 2019
- · Performed survey research on the modal shift in transportation and developed a predictive model for a governmental body and an inland port
- · Advised a private company active in the entertainment industry on the design of a data asset repository
- Constructed a financial model for a mid-scale mobility management project

Capgemini Invent Brussels, BE

CONSULTANT (DATA GOVERNANCE)

Sep. 2017 - Sep. 2018

- · Performed a benchmark study of data governance operating models in financial services
- · Developed and optimised various data asset documentation processes in the context of BCBS239 and GDPR regulatory frameworks
- Conducted a data quality maturity assessment across various business and functional departments within a major Belgian bank
- Set up data-sharing agreements between various business and functional departments within a major Belgian bank

INTERNSHIPS (FULL-TIME)

MANAGEMENT CONSULTANT

HR CONSULTANT

CEMAC Ghent, BE

Redesign of the firm's organisational structure and internal business processes

May 2017 - Jun. 2017

Sep. 2015 - Jan. 2016

Analysis of the firm's product strategy and internationalisation opportunities and capabilities

The Future Alliance Ghent. BE

- Organised assessment and development centres for middle management candidates
- Organised workshops concerning HR-related topics (e.g. giving and receiving feedback)
- · Carried out recruitment and selection assignments for entry and (middle) management functions

Hudson Ghent, BE

HR CONSULTANT Oct. 2014 - Nov. 2014

Developed 40 rating scales, including a manual, for the advisory firm's dedicated competency model

SOCIAL SECTOR (PART-TIME)

180 Degrees Consulting (180DC)

Ghent BF

- 180DC is the world's largest international consultancy for non-profits and social enterprises
- Led the human capital activities of 180DC's Ghent University branch
- Conducted selection tests, incl. reasoning tests and structured interviews, of about 70 university students
- Other activities: implementation of 180° feedback system, social media marketing, event support

180 Degrees Consulting

Ghent, BE

MANAGEMENT CONSULTANT

HUMAN CAPITAL DIRECTOR

Mar. 2015 - Jun. 2015

Jul. 2015 - Jun. 2016

- · Co-developed an integrated fundraising and marketing strategy for the NGO Join For Water
- Conducted survey research regarding the brand perceptions of Join For Water's donors and sympathizers
- · Developed an evidence-based, bespoke brand personality for Join For Water, as well as brand improvement guidelines

Education

Ghent University Ghent RF

Aug. 2019 - Present PhD. Economics

- Doctoral courses: Econometrics, Advanced Econometrics (Non-Linear Techniques), Labour Economics, Multilevel Analysis
- Other courses: Advanced Academic Writing in English, Multilevel Analysis in R, Generalised Linear Models in R, Multidisciplinary Research Tools to Study Work and the Labour Market, Effective Graphical Displays
- Supervisors: Prof. Stijn Baert, Prof. Eva Derous

Vrije Universiteit Brussel Brussels, BE

Aug. 2019 - Present PhD. Sociology

Supervisor: Prof. Pieter-Paul Verhaeghe (Joint PhD with UGent as the main institution)

Vlerick Business School Ghent, BE

MM, GENERAL MANAGEMENT (MAGNA CUM LAUDE)

Sep. 2016 - Jun. 2017

- · Key Courses: Corporate Finance, Financial Accounting, Management Accounting and Control, Strategic Management, Operations Management
- · Electives: Big Data and Data Analytics, Digital Strategy (w/ BNPP Fortis), Strategy and Organisational Design, Mergers and Acquisitions (w/ Gimv)
- Bootcamp: Strategic Innovation in Renewable Energy (w/ Durabilis)

Ghent University Ghent, BF

MSc, Industrial and Organisational Psychology (Magna Cum Laude)

Sep. 2011 - Jun. 2016

- Key Courses: Multi-level Organisational Research, Statistics, Applied Data Analysis, Human Resource Management, Industrial Relations
- Master's thesis: Short form of the Wilde Intelligenztest: Psychometric qualities and utility of a 12-minute intelligence test for personnel selection

Publications

PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

Applied Economics Letters 2022

Ethnic discrimination on paper: Uncovering realtors' willingness to discriminate with mystery mails

A Ghekiere, L Lippens, S Baert, PP Verhaeghe

Journal of Ethnic and Migration Studies

Is labour market discrimination against ethnic minorities better explained by taste or statistics? A systematic review of the empirical evidence

L Lippens, S Baert, A Ghekiere, PP Verhaeghe, E Derous

2021 **Economics Letters**

Loss aversion in taste-based employee discrimination: Evidence from a choice experiment

L Lippens, S Baert, E Derous

2021 **PLOS ONE**

2022

How do employees think the COVID-19 crisis will affect their careers?

L Lippens, E Moens, P Sterkens, J Weytjens, S Baert

The European Journal of Health Economics 2021

The COVID-19 crisis and telework: A research survey on experiences, expectations and hopes

E Moens, L Lippens, P Sterkens, J Weytjens, S Baert

TECHNICAL REPORTS

2022	Ghent University
	SUGAW 4: Inactiviteit in Europa en de Belgische gewesten
	S Baert, L Lippens
2022	Ghent University
	SUGAW 5: Inactiviteit onder migranten in België
	S Baert, E Derous, B George, L Lippens, G Van Hoye, B Neyt, S Van Hoof
2022	Ghent University
	SUGAW 6: Welzijn op het werk in Vlaanderen
	S Baert, E Clays, E Derous, K du Bois, L Lippens, S Mertens, B Neyt,
2021	Ghent University
	Discriminatie op de Gentse arbeidsmarkt anno 2021: rapportering
	S Baert, A Dalle, L Lippens, L Malfait
2021	Ghent University
	Nulmeting discriminatie op de Antwerpse arbeidsmarkt: rapportering

S Baert, A Dalle, L Lippens, L Malfait, A Sharipova

DISCUSSION PAPERS

IZA Institute of Labour Economics
 Selecting names for experiments on ethnic discrimination
 S Baert, L Lippens, H Van Borm
 IZA Institute of Labour Economics
 The state of hiring discrimination: A meta-analysis of (almost) all recent correspondence experiments
 L Lippens, S Vermeiren, S Baert

Visit my Google Scholar profile at https://bit.ly/louis-lippens-scholar for a comprehensive overview of my research.

Services and Outreach __

PEER REVIEWS

In addition to conducting my own research, I have also reviewed the work of some of my peers. I have served as a reviewer (ad hoc) for the Journal of Labor Economics (1), Technology in Society (1), Journal of Ethnic and Migration Studies (1), Social Science & Medicine (1), Social Forces (1), PLOS ONE (2), Journal of Sociology (1), Work and Occupations (1), Social Policy and Society (1), International Migration Review (1), Oxford Bulletin of Economics and Statistics (1), International Journal of Manpower (1), and Economics Bulletin (2).

ACADEMIC OUTREACH

2022	CESSMIR Conference	Ghent, BE	
2022	Understanding ethnic hiring discrimination: A contextual analysis of empirical evidence IMISCOE Annual Conference	Oolo NO	
	The state of hiring discrimination: A meta-analysis of (almost) all recent correspondence experiments	Oslo, NO	
2022	Spring Meeting of Young Economists	Orléans, FR	
	The state of hiring discrimination: A meta-analysis of (almost) all recent correspondence experiments	Oneuns, r K	
2021	CESSMIR Conference	Ghent, BE	
	The state of hiring discrimination: A meta-analysis of (almost) all recent correspondence experiments	Offerit, DE	
2021	EALE Annual Conference	Barcelona, ES	
	Is labour market discrimination against ethnic minorities better explained by taste or statistics?	(online)	
2021	Day of Sociology	Utrecht, NL	
	Taste-based discrimination: Actually a matter of contact avoidance?	(online)	
2021	CESSMIR Research Day	Ghent, BE	
	Taste-based discrimination: Actually a matter of contact avoidance?	OHEIR, DL	
2021	Faculty of Economics and Business Administration Research Day	Ghent, BE	
	Loss aversion in taste-based employee discrimination: Evidence from a choice experiment	Offerit, DE	
2020	Context Matters Symposium	Brussels, BE	
	Is labour market discrimination against ethnic minorities better explained by taste or statistics?	DIUSSEIS, DE	

SOCIETAL OUTREACH

2022	UGent @ Work	Blog post	
	Measuring intentions to discriminate: in writing, open and exposed	ыод розг	
2022	UGent @ Work	Blog post	
	Ethnic labour market discrimination: Generalisation or aversion?	blog post	
2022	HR Magazine	Magazino articlo	
	The structured interview best predicts a good match	Magazine article	
2022	LinkedIn	Plagnost	
	The top-ranked selection tools to hire the best-performing candidate	Blog post	
2021	Het Laatste Nieuws	Nowspapar articla	
	Older applicants face greater hiring discrimination than ethnic minority applicants worldwide	Newspaper article	
2021	Trends (magazine)	Nowspapar article	
	Hiring discrimination based on age is worse than ethnic hiring discrimination	Newspaper article	
2021	UGent @ Work		
	Does discrimination have a price?	Blog post	
2021	Radio 1, Nieuwe Feiten	Radio interview	
	Does discrimination have a price?	Radio IIItei view	
2020	Apache	Newspaper article	
	Trainings against labour market discrimination	Newspaper article	
2020	Het Laatste Nieuws		
	My job disappears, my pay gets smaller, my promotion gets snubbed: This is how the Flemish people think	Newspaper article	
	about their work future		

Skills_____

GENERAL SKILLS

Research	Analytics	Business
Audit studies – Survey research – Experimental research – Applied psychometrics	(Ordered) logit models – Linear models – Meta-analysis – Meta-regression – Reliability and validity analysis – Structural equation modeling	Project management – Human capital management – Corporate finance – Consultancy

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Coding Languages	Research Software	Business Software	Creative Software	Other
R (ggplot2, tidyverse, hugo, xaringan, quarto) – SQL	RStudio – Stata – SPSS – Knime	Collibra – MS Office	Photoshop – GIMP – Ableton Live	Git – Markdown – LaTeX

LANGUAGES

Skill	Dutch	English	French
Reading	C2	C2	C1
Writing	C2	C2	B1
Listening	C2	C2	B2
Speaking	C2	C1	B1

Note. CEFR: A1/A2: Basic User; B1/B2: Independent User; C1/C2: Proficient User.

Certificates

2019	Exploratory Data Analysis (Johns Hopkins University)	Coursera
2018	Reproducible Research (Johns Hopkins University)	Coursera
2019	R Programming (Johns Hopkins University)	Coursera
2017	Financial Markets (Yale University)	Coursera
2017	Fundamentals of Quantitative Modeling (Wharton School)	Coursera
2017 2017	Collibra Community Manager Collibra Data Steward	Collibra Collibra

Honors and Awards

2017 Student Achievement for Outstanding Performance

Personal recognition for obtaining the most and highest positive peer evaluations in group assignments throughout the academic year.

Vlerick Business School

2015 Best European Consulting Branch

180 Degrees Consulting Ghent was named the best overall European branch (Europe) of the world's largest consultancy for non-profits and social enterprises. We were lauded for our collaboration-fostering spirit, high client focus and professional approach to private partnerships.

180 Degrees Consulting

Trivia

Sucker for R

I am a sucker for everything related to R (ggplot2, Shiny, Xaringan...), my go-to environment for statistical computing. The content of this very resume is written in R, using R Markdown, the {{vitae}} package, and some LaTeX typesetting.

Passionate about electronic music

I have been playing the piano since I was 9 years old, albeit much less frequently in the past few years. Moreover, between the ages of 15 and 22, I was active as an electronic music artist, producer, and event manager.

Fond of the sea

As a teenager, I longed to spend my summer vacations at the seaside. From my 18th birthday onwards, after an intensive year of training, I was able to combine this fondness for the sea with a student job as a lifeguard at the Belgian coast for 6 consecutive summers.